[Music]
[Laughter]
I I always have been doing since my
childhood a bit of urban exploration so
I love to like break to a window of an
abandoned Factory or building or train
station so that's one of my hobbies used
to be what's on the roofs of buildings
you know what's uh uh what's in an
abandoned building seller and in a
factory we did a lot of work on this
ciz
stabilized at the time when I um did my
first photo shoot of the AER elad
station it was under construction but
then there was no security guards no
fences even you can just walk and see
the broken textures and layers of paint
and brick and history and uh it was just
so cool that I can get and get this
information before it got overbuilt with
a new neighborhood I went to check it
out last night and it happens to be
completely destroyed and under
construction again and it just goes back
luckily
coincidentally uh to the exact same
state where I shot it 25 years ago
actually
[Music]
oh
h
[Music]
so one of the big challenges with
halflife was just establishing the
company and sort of determining whether
not we could actually make video games
at all like my background was operating
systems and spreadsheets Mike Harrington
who was the co-founder had a similar
background he had a little more game
experience than I did but with halflife
you know we were pretty sure we were
going to fail and then halflife was
successful it was like a lot more
successful than we had any reason to
expect and now we had to follow it up
right we we didn't want to have a
sophomore slump we didn't want to be a
you know a one and and and done kind of
company so now we had the terrifying
obligation to our customers and to our
fans to to somehow Advance our game
design skills our technology uh all
needed to level up for for the second
game I think a bunch of us were really
shocked by the success of halflife one
we were this young unproven company I
don't think any of us really knew what
to expect when we finished the game I
remember when we started working on
halflife 2 we had already set the bar
pretty high for ourselves so during
halflife 2 what we were really trying to
do is take advantage of the visibility
that Half-Life had created for us in the
industry to continue to hire the best
people that we could find in the world
it just got easier the bar didn't get
any lower but the fact that we had you
know it went from hey this weird dude
who worked on operating systems wants to
convince you he can run a game company
to oh halflife won a bunch of awards and
now they're working on a sequel to that
it even was my first week or my first
day um was actually the going away party
for Mike Harrington the co-founder yeah
I came to Val when I was just tiny uh we
had I think or maybe 10 10 or so people
Dave and I grew up together uh in
Louisiana so he and I had always talked
about maybe starting a game company at
some point and during halflife that kind
of changed to a maybe instead of that we
the the dream could be you come and work
here at this one you know with me yeah
you know and I interviewed the day that
halflife went gold and I took the team
photo of was like an old photo of us we
broke a papier-mâché head crab and
everything yeah I was freaking out yeah
I was actually working on a video game
Concept in high school and I was seeking
a mentor and I got in touch with Mark
glad law at valve I guess it was the
right time in right place and quite a
bit of luck and I ended up getting
internship that way I guess I was at the
time so you've got a whole company that
that's familiar with tools and a whole
process and then we just started over
like we rebuilt the tools and we rebuilt
the engine so we had this long period of
time where we could sort of take our
time on design and so we spent a lot of
time working on story and just trying to
figure out how to make this thing bigger
like somehow more epic and those
discussions eventually led to
this idea that so in halflife one you
open this portal some strange Rift to
another dimension we thought well what
if that broadcasts the signal to the
universe that's like oh there's this
planet there it's free air and water and
so then we sort of came up with this
idea of well there's this Mega
organization that's resource starved and
they're just going to come and
take it if they can how many years
passed between six yeah so I would say
the first two
years we tried a lot of things and a lot
of those story arcs that we had
initially didn't have really any
carryover from black Mesa or any of that
there was originally going to be three
three different alien races like the
bugs or religious ones and the ant lions
actually came out of that bug race That
was supposed to be a much bigger part of
of the game it had three alien races the
the warrior aliens the insect aliens and
the um spy aliens and it had like a prag
likee city which ended up being the
closest thing to City 17 in a lot of
ways it reminds me of writing music you
know everyone was sort of riffing ideas
on what if we did this or tried that I
remember we were really ambitious at the
beginning I remember we designed what
four cities at one point Prague
Jerusalem Chicago
uh Los Angeles I believe we had an
Arctic Base an underwater base an
icebreaker ship an airplane sequence
that crashed into a highrise which we
cut right after 911 we had uh several
combine bases in the Wasteland we had
the air exchange which is where they
were taking you know the atmosphere from
Earth we had uh train depot and so on so
we really obviously had to scale back
what we were trying to do but uh you
know that's okay to go a little bit nuts
at the beginning I I saw it almost as
like sophomore anxiety maybe you know
like oh wow we have to like we have to
surpass halflife and halflife was
important you know and and and so it was
like this like unbounded ambition and we
kept asking ourselves and Gabe K kept
asking well how is this halflife you
know when you have a silent first person
narrator you could you could tell people
this is Gordon and throw that character
into literally any environment say yeah
this is halflife but if unless the
environment is telling you that that's
the case you're not it's very arbitrary
so we we wrestled with that a long time
slowly the sort of grab bag of
characters we had we started to feel
like there was connections between them
and then at some point we realized oh
this is we can make this out of the
science team the survivors from black
Mesa and suddenly that the IDE for me it
was the idea of it's a science team that
suddenly you could put those guys
anywhere and because they have like a
familial
interconnectedness and they recognize
Gordon that will make you feel like it's
a continuation of the story like
obviously Alex was totally new to that
universe but she had a father who had
been in Black Mesa and he and the other
scientists were friends and had extended
their relationship into this new world
that you were in that was kind of the
click was the science team and that was
a while till we got there you know much
like the first one where all the
contributors were really uh collectively
deciding on the direction is we were
really making a push to grow the team
and hire new artists you know zabi ing
was an influential um early contributor
I think you know he and I were doing
character designs for Gordon and for
Alex and for some of the antagonist
combine characters at the time I was
looking at a lot of um I mean really the
helmets which I think are kind of one of
their defining features was based off
some gas masks from Europe that I had
seen in some reference I remember uh
doing early concepts of the new HV suit
like what's Gordon going to be now and I
had kind of just started and so I was
like I'm going to make this my own it
looked I guess guess kind of like the
still suits in Dune but black and a lot
more belt buckles and latex and Gabe was
just kind of like what's this like it's
Gordon I was like really proud and
excited he like why is it not orange you
know it's like or some something to that
effect of essentially like why are you
giving up this iconic part of of the
character people love it yeah people
love that so what are you doing and it's
like you know I kind of I was like yeah
I guess he's right so we kind of went
back to the drawing board and and ended
up with what what shipped and we had
like I don't know so many creatures that
we tried and and abandoned you know not
because they were bad because we had
better things to pursue you know more
like there were the sacx the cremator
the crab synth um stalkers stalkers we
had a little bit in the game yeah we
shipped the stalkers but not as an
adversary that you fought yeah there was
there was definitely an evolution of um
how biological versus how synthetic a
lot of the the creatures in halflife 2
were and uh I was always hoping to get
to a space where it was ambiguous you
know where you could quite tell if this
was created or if it had grown or if it
was natural or synthetic there was some
since I did that never shipped actually
we we did ship them they were at the end
of the game when you're going through
the Citadel I had designed these scents
that no animator could figure out how to
actually move cuz they weren't built to
move and much like some of the
environments that we've seen you know
released in the leak that were very dark
some of the early Half-Life stuff was
also very dark but at the Time video
games were very dark in the interim
before we hired Fletcher and before
Victor was there because it was the old
environments right I don't remember how
it came about that they built this level
but the idea was there was some looting
going on and the idea was you're in this
little alley and you see a citizen you
hear a voice saying TVs free TVs like
they just got into the TV store and
there's the citizens and the cops are
fighting and you see a citizen run past
you holding a TV set and he goes get one
get a TV get yourself a TV and then he
runs off to the thing and you go in
another cour Courtyard and there's a cop
with a night stick and a citizen and
they're like having a fist fight and
then it's interesting because the NPCs
are negotiating their bounding boxes and
there's some animation like the how
difficult it is to contact uh we
captured everything we took pictures of
whiteboard design sessions there were
really crude drawings and ideas some of
the stuff from the very beginning made
it all the way to the end you know um
Raven home ant lions dog kleiner's pet
head crab and you know those things were
just so fun in the moment that how could
they not survive right the other thing
that was really memorable is I remember
we started making the world really
dystopian really dark at the beginning
and some of the concept art shows that
we didn't think players would enjoy
spending 20 to 40 hours in such a dark
and kind of oppressive setting so the
game lightened up considerably over time
but you know still maintain the the
feeling of a Security State so I I was
trying to like get all these cool ideas
that the team had already when I arrived
and streamlined them you know instantly
I think we were friends with Mark ladw
we had a common sort of vision and and
and fantasy to create a Orwell like City
and then slowly you know I brought
context behind that the idea that we can
place this in an anonymous central
eastern European city which is a perfect
setting because you know in in these
countries there were so many waves of
invasions you know we had the otoman
Empire we had the Russians and now why
not the aliens and one of the first Maps
I remember working on was they called
testam standards on half life uh every
level designer kind of had their own
idea of how big stairs were or how big
steps were going to be or how big a
button was make sure we had some
consistency another thing that was sort
of important was just getting more
people to go on field trips and going to
do research because I think a lot of the
level designers on halflife one you know
just were building very abstractly and
so we wanted to have some more grounding
in reality and have more realistic
proportions and also just get textures
were going from hand painted to more
photographic and so we would go out and
collect a lot of the pictures for those
uh textures to start um building for a
new library I joined halflife 2 probably
a year after it had
started um I know that it was at least a
year because I was put on Borealis which
was like everybody else had
disowned um but then I came along and
said oh well I guess this is now your
problem um so I started on Borealis and
of course I failed at that too that
eventually got cut yeah so I came in um
having had experience doing a game AI uh
I was at Looking Glass Studios um
probably the biggest thing I there was a
lead program on thief the Dark Project
the for AI for that too uh and actually
my first thing is they handed Borealis
to me uh to do the after I'd finished to
yeah to do the um the the uh the AI for
the the uh the guy that you're supposed
to walk through the Boreal ship with
there was a bunch of work put into it we
even went on an icebreaker ship uh to
get reference as soon as we started to
put it together we realized how
unbelievably tight the space was and you
could never make any kind of really
interesting combat in it and so it just
withered on the vine right there I mean
when I started there was that document
that was the tech wish list it was just
this very barebones bullet list of tech
features and I mean I think it was like
six years of work to build that Tech
list and and then realize it into a
product and leverage all the
implications of it you know so this was
a main feature that the light felt very
very realistic and
intuitive uh because of the source
engine and the work the collaboration
between artist and Engineers Ken
Birdwell uh and he was a fan about
photography and getting the the lighting
right the math that we were using was
wrong and not only that the math that
everybody was using was wrong
and then as I started to correct it and
I realized just how bad it was and then
I fixed it and suddenly everything
looked great I had to go tell the
hardware guys the people who made
Hardware accelerators that fundamentally
the math was wrong on their cards that
took about two and a half years I could
not convince the guys finally we hired
Gary mcard and Charlie Brown and those
guys had enough pull and enough I have a
fine arts major nobody's going to listen
to me uh Charlie and I met at college at
the University of Florida we were both
getting computer science degrees yes I
ended up dropping out uh to go work at
3dfx as employee 11 there and then I
think Charlie you actually graduated
didn't you I graduated and Then followed
you and I was 17 there yeah proba 17
there were three kind of principles one
was to make something that was immersive
uh visually uh really rich and appealing
something more like you would see in a
film and uh the art Direction and the
technology to make that happen second
one was to have characters that you
cared about so basically that could
react emote that mattered in the world
instead of just uh being signposts third
was to have um a responsive environment
with physics that mattered I think that
I maybe more than other people realized
just how big of a task we were setting
for ourselves like so I was a little bit
daunted by that we felt the pressure
from Gabe actually to to double down and
make something even grander than
halflife 1 there in lies the sort a
little bit of the Trap of halflife 2's
development story which went from being
a pretty quick like let's figure out how
to do this to like a six-year you know
slog yeah and it was like you know six
seven days a week you know 10 to 14
hours a day yeah we're going to cut your
feature sorry it's just not worth it so
I ended up being really the point person
working with the FBI I I remember coming
in that morning and figuring it out and
it just felt like someone had just
punched me in the gut uh what this mean
like can we still keep working on the
game like is someone just going to
release the whole game tomorrow I
definitely was not shielded from that
you know there I remember one
conversation with Gabe which is like he
was like so how [__] are we yeah we're
kind of screwed the company was pretty
close to going bankrupt I was pretty
close to going personally bankrupt it's
like there was no money left I can't
think of another case when that happened
yeah a real [__] move are we alled
to cry in this documentary that's what I
want to know
[Music]
[Laughter]
remember we shipped halflife one and you
know the world loved it and every we're
just super happy like yeah we did this
thing and and we had a big meeting and
Gabe looks at me and goes like so all
the animations are
terrible how how how are you going to
make halflife 2 better in halflife 1 we
got we we made what were at the time
significant improvements but still they
were they were fairly robotic and
mechanical and so we had to go and do a
huge amount of work on the animation
system and on the facial animation
system and coming up with authoring
tools that allowed you to do it
well end of the
line the a lot of this was level
designer design like figuring out how to
build atmosphere we knew that we wanted
to start off seen the Citadel right away
um and we wanted to introduce you to the
city with this great voice acting from
Robert CP we wanted to finally do real
characters we knew that from halflife
one the way that players would respond
to having any character talk to them was
like Way Beyond the reaction that we
expected like when we figured this out
in play testing like if Barney would
follow you around and shoot things you
just suddenly you just love this guy and
you love this scientist you love these
characters so we knew we wanted to just
bring that like way up to the next like
levels beyond what we could
imagine and the theory was if we could
make a character who could act
realistically that that would help the
player make an emotional connection to
the other characters in the game and at
the time we decided we were going to do
that not only did none of the technology
work but I would go talk to Industry
professionals and they would tell me not
to bother cuz you couldn't do it luckily
found a a a research work done in the
70s by Dr Paul emman and he had just
broken down how the face works and how
humans make expressions and he had this
incredibly wonderful formal clinical
description of what a face does and the
sorts of things that normal people do
with their face I tried this experiment
with putting a grid on Scott Lynch's
face um and uh shooting him from the
front and the side so that we could get
points from this Grid in three space for
the geometry and we got uh shots of his
texture and we found a good way to model
that a reasonable head you know the of
his geometry and then uh project the
texture onto it and then abstract it or
stylize it enough so that it it didn't
look totally photographic but it it
looked like a kind of a real person
occasionally when somebody hears the
history it will you know generate a
light bulb but no no I don't get
accosted no one's asking you for beers
or anything no no or buying me
beers we added Ken's uh itch to that
which was amazing because he really
modeled and he went deep into the
research of how eyes work eyeballs was
about nine months just on eyeballs and
and uh but you have to do each step you
have to get the shape of the eye right
you have to get how the eyelid gets
pushed by the cornea and the ball of the
eye so as your eyes move around all you
know the your lower lid your upper lid
all of those get sh shifted slightly and
it's all
automatic uh it was wonderful the day I
got at working the characters went from
looking like interesting dolls to Alex
just looked at me oh my God this is
working they would ask for surprising
things at times uh like they wanted
really find control over looking at
named objects in the 3D World no matter
what direction the actor is facing so
you had to figure out things about oh
maybe the upper body needs to turn and
the head needs to turn and the eyes need
to turn um so we're in the elevator
coming back from Starbucks to get
morning coffee and we saw this face and
it's like that's him that's the
scientist and he was an accountant in uh
The Firm below ours in Kirkland well
nothing uh kind of blows your mind when
you've been working all day on this
character in your game and all sudden
you get on the elevator you're like holy
crap it's him I I once ran into him at
the airport so we cast people that were
um real change vendors in front of
supermarkets we cast waiters in
restaurants when I was in junior high
school I took Kate classes um and that
was my old karate instructor Randy line
said hey there is a guy holding a sign
for work at this exit on 520 every day
who has this great face and he took a
picture of his face you know he stopped
and asked if he could and so it's like
oh this is great I think this guy's Eli
you know we brought him in and you know
paid him a couple hundred dollars which
is what we were paying people back then
and so that's that's where he came from
erine gich was a Bosnian friend from
that we I knew from school he was like
we want the East European contingent and
stuff too so it was pretty interesting
we wanted anybody uh to feel a part of
the world when they're playing it as
player and so you know we found people
from pretty much every skin color
different ages uh male and female equal
numbers of males and females sadly for
them they all had to share the same
voice
actor sadly for us too we dropped a
crate of rockets coming across the plaza
we hoped for one more fighter to help
storm that barricade we never dreamed it
would be you m cliner lab was the first
prototype that we did of of how
characters could work together together
in a scene yeah it was like a proof of
concept we kind of had to make that work
you know and and put everything we could
into it at the time to test all the
technology and then know from there what
can we do what else can we do with this
turning into a performance that would be
engaging rather than just audio radio
play kind of thing yeah I mean that was
the point where that that scene was
where it all started to come together
all our theories and hopes for what the
experience might be and it all went
completely smoothly
out of the box it was amazing the most
difficult technical aspects are really
kind of boring they're the okay the
character is running through Ai and now
they need to jump in and do you know hug
another character now they need to pick
up something from the desk and that
thing on the desk can move and where the
character is can move and where the
player is can move and everything about
this whole scene can move dynamically
and to get to that stage where it just
looks right is this huge technical
Challenge and artistic challenge but
once it's done it's just it's just
[Music]
amazing
Gordon Gordon snap out of
it you're staring at me
again ah warming up nicely are you sure
you don't want me to swap out the
polarizer I remember uh when we got
Fletcher on and he would kind of teach
us about how they did things at Disney
and they would bring in acting coaches
for the animators what does sarcasm look
like certain expressions and there's a
timing to those expressions and when you
have a scene with multiple characters
it's not always the person talking
that's doing the acting right
everybody's acting you know even though
you may be looking at Kleiner because
he's the one talking every character in
that scene around you behind you they're
all doing stuff because not everybody's
going to be looking at the same place
yeah I remember even just like when Alex
telep
and then you see her show up on the
screen right oh that was incredible
heads over gives him a quick gives him a
quick kiss and what like it it tells you
so much about the relationship without
having to say hi Dad I love you and all
this extra like heavy heavy handed stuff
so Jake was a random demo real that was
sent in that was
incredible uh Jake was incredible Jake
was incredible like Miss that guy one of
a kind yeah miss that guy amazing a
technical animator yeah I mean Jake was
one of those guys that um you know
whatever needed to be done he would
figure it out and just make it happen
you know it'll just get done correctly I
think also the the context of when all
this was taking place like the problems
that he was helping solve were just
things that weren't being done even
something as simple as passing passing
someone an object between two characters
was sounds super simple but actually
really complex especially back then and
so he he really helped push like how do
we how do we even do this uh in
collaboration with the programmers zie
wanted to do a a goo thing uh so I
worked on the Shader for that um I did
the stuff for rendering that and all the
little monitors everywhere that that
showed other scenes did the refraction
shaders and the code the supporting code
for that the shaders didn't really have
conditionals or Loops or anything like
that so we would unroll it all and
compile a bazillion shaders uh it got to
the point where it was so many shaders
and it took so long to compile that we
um I think Mike dult implemented um
distributed building uh system
everyone's machine in the company was
running something that could sit there
and compile shaders all the time or do
lighting for the levels or whatever it's
all like any opportunity to kind of add
to the visual storytelling I think was
yeah and I think we hid the first Gman
sighting
he was one that's right he was one of
the monitor it would flip to him yeah
yeah and then he just walk out of frame
the moment where you see him makes you
realize there must be a lot of moments
where you didn't know he was watching
you he's not big brother that that that
doesn't make sense to me that he would
be a big brother because that's sort of
industrial and and bureaucratic and this
is much more intimate he's always over
your
shoulder
watching
waiting for the moment
to
speak that's where I think he lives my
name is Mike Shapiro and I am Gman I am
also Barney and you know Barney's not
he's he's not that far from you know G
Gordon like he's not that far from where
I live you know he's so fallible and and
and you he's always tripping over
himself and that he's just such a good
guy you know not necessarily the most
capable but just really there for you
get that thing away from me here my pet
hop up I think early on I had a sense
that Gman knew a lot and was taking care
of a lot that we didn't quite understand
was kind of enjoying [__] with people
and massaging reality in a way that he
had a unique capacity to do there were
also aspects to him that I knew pretty
early on like his relationship to time
is very different than you or I would
think in my mind he could literally be
in two places at once and so sometimes
there was a kind of a an
implied hitch in his timing or he's
experiencing two or three different
moments at once and that might be funny
for a reason that you don't know cuz
you're only in one time with him at at a
moment the right man in the wrong place
place can make all the difference in the
world I think as we want as we realized
how well she worked coming out of stuff
like the kleiner's lab experience we
started looking for more and more ways
to include her in stuff and and of
course you really came to life when we
found Merl dandd yeah we can feel her
already as a partner in creating this
character I think coming out of that
she's just got a creative relationship
with this character and she's going to
bring a lot to it I feel like she was
really able to bring a warmth and humor
into her deliveries too that other
people it was more like like soldier in
a game a little bit I mean she did this
great job of bringing like a a character
warmth into it and now we're sitting
ducks unless we can get this thing
running come on Dr Kleiner is it going
to work or not no no there's nothing to
be nervous about let's see the massless
field flux your self liit and I've
clamped my name is Harry Robbins I'm
known as H Robins I have a stage name of
Dr Hal uh my only doctorate is in
theology from the church of the
subgenius which I'm involved in well um
I think perhaps Mark was familiar with
the things I do on the radio and he
thought my voice would be good for it uh
I have a monthly ask Dr Hal show on
Twitch and zoom and I'm also on a couple
of radio shows well I'm a graphic artist
I've worked for DC Comics for their
Paradox press line well I have some
patrons who I do painting for I've
painted many things for them I played Dr
Isaac Kleiner uh after I did the voice
of a number of different scientists I
try to pronounce all the words uh I make
sure to aspirate consonants for example
I don't say didn't the way most people
do even newscasters today I always make
sure to say didn't perhaps it sounds
archaic that way Mark wrote archaic
Expressions into my dialogue and I would
say things like Ohi and so forth no not
up there no no careful lar those are
quite
fragile oh F it'll be another week
before I can coax her out there yeah
longer if we're lucky Barney you're not
an animal person it was always Pleasant
I was always well treated they were
always patient even if I mispronounced
uh something which was obvious they
would correct me and I would pay
attention and I always try to be as
close as possible to a one take Wonder
so they don't have to do it again but
that enabled them to do it many times
and so they had a lot of things which
arose from that and some of these are
the things I'm asked to say by fans
which uh are inexplicable to people who
don't know the game like you want this
guy to say have you seen my coffee cup
and why do we all have to wear these
ridiculous
[Music]
ties so in the same way that uh we
thought it was important in halflife one
that when you shot a wall that you know
you we put decals on the to indicate
that you shot it we wanted to say okay
what happens when you throw a grenade at
a bunch of boxes right the world itself
needed to be more um reactive to
everything you did we used some third
party code but Jay Stelly was the one
who really wrote the rapper on that that
integrated it and physics was even even
uh early in the project was pretty
successful right once we got over the
initial thing of like things falling
over and we started adding breakable
objects you could things you could
script and Hammer um we added vehicles
sound cues from all the objects and the
AI you could drop things on them and
crush them things like that all those
behaviors uh once we got just a few of
those things in that was really fertile
for real everyone who worked on halflife
2 Mass has got broken down into a set of
scales that I assume someone's already
talked about no okay well you see so
yeah all right so there the question is
whether it's bigger than a bread box or
smaller than a space station right like
when you when went to debug something
and the text saids oh this thing weighs
as much as a racehorse yeah you knew it
was more than a bread box not as much as
a space station I think so but I don't
know in the scale if it's closer to this
or closer to that yeah cuz refrigerator
yeah oh refrigerator this all came from
at some point I think it was David sper
so you could look at any entity in the
game and turn on a bunch of debug and
text about it and one of the most
important things to get right in every
object in the game that was physically
simulated was Mass cuz that dictated an
enormous amount of things like amount of
force it would you know apply to
something else when it impact when it
hit them amount of for you know it's
it's response when it's hit by something
else all that had to get it right but of
course like mass is it's just a number
like what does this mean to anyone and
so I think it was David Spire who found
online some list of masses and objects
and he just made just brought that into
the game so that when you looked at an
object it' say like 100 bracket
racehorse or something so over time like
you all just got that locked in and
because it was like in you know a
logarithmic scale you it went from
things like you know breadbox paint can
or something up to like space station
the Moon the Moon like what what do I do
with this at this point it's just key
frame at that point yeah so there would
be many like conversations where we'd
say so I don't know do you think that's
more like a racehorse or or or the speed
station the the very first physics
puzzle that we put in the game you know
from a develop M calendar standpoint was
the uh the washing machine puzzle where
you push the washing machine into the
hopper and raise the ramp for the
Airboat to jump over we developed that
because we felt like we had this section
of Relentless pressure with the attack
helicopter watching players play test we
felt like they needed relief from it you
you see the very first training of it in
the um on foot canals with the Teeter
Totter that you have to put the cinder
blocks on um which came which was added
to the game later
uh and it sort of training of like hey
you can interact with levers and balance
and uh you know create paths for
yourself and then yeah later the
buoyancy puzzle we added that one after
the washing machine puzzle and it was
just kind of like oh you can you can
connect masses with invisible uh pulley
systems and then build little machines
that
way I guess at first right the gravity
gun was kind of this we weren't even
sure we were going to sh it in the game
it was like a development tool and so it
was like this beam you could reach out
and grab things and P pull them toward
you or reposition them you know drop
them grab them from another point but
then uh we talked about simplifying it
and just making it to where it was just
pushing on things and pulling on things
and where could we go with that and the
first the first draft of Raven Holm
wasn't really about physics so deeply
right we ended up reorganizing the game
to put ravenol after you get the gravity
gun originally it was before tour you
would um Park the Airboat at the dock of
Raven Holm and then get out and go
explore Raven
[Music]
Holm we wanted like a horror area since
in a lot of ways halflife was a horror
game and the horror was kind of leeching
out of halflife 2 so we at least wanted
one environment that was just scary and
then we had a design meeting where Doug
Woods said you know preacher with a
shotgun and I was like oh yes the
important thing to know is like we
didn't sit down and design Raven home as
like the tutorial for all those things
it it kind of kept getting things over
time uh and then after we got more
physics working uh we had this idea that
there would be traps uh for the zombies
in there that were physics and there
were a bunch of them uh and they didn't
all make it into the the final game and
then some of them did work though and uh
you know we had to build system for
cutting the zombies in half once we
added the the uh propeller traps and we
had to make them the right height so you
could crawl under them or the zombies
could crawl under them and then someone
had the idea well what if the top half
can keep going and it can get you under
there you know we tried that and that
was great uh someone had the idea of saw
blade and ravenholm like already existed
and we ended up like based on this
Behavior happening in another level like
built the saw blade and went and put it
back in ravenol Raven home is probably
some of the most fun I had working on
halflife 2 the whole idea behind ravenol
and that we were going to starve you of
ammo sort of force them into a position
where they have to rely on on physics
and uh the context of the objects around
them it's like oh wouldn't it be awesome
if this zombie who it's going to take
him 30 more seconds to get to me but
he's got like a barrel right there like
what if he could swap that at me so that
was definitely something that was just
like we have physics now um this would
be a cool thing to do with it and it' be
a thing that would make sense and a
thing that would be scary and fun one of
things that was like extremely strong at
was little touches like um I think we
called them puzzlets we did call them
puzzlets like they weren't puzzles they
were puzzlets yeah it's this little
thing that takes you between 5 and 60
seconds to resolve and at the end you
either get something or you feel a
certain way and uh it was really a big
part of making sure that like minute to-
minute gameplay as we called it was was
interesting yeah he was good at
that we actually did this as an exercise
of like okay take you know all the
elements in the game and and have a grid
of you know rows and Columns of all
those elements and make sure that
there's a meaningful thing at each
intersection of of of those cells so
that everything has a meaningful
interaction with everything else and
where we saw empty cells we would
actually design a thing there something
we could do there yeah Barnacles plus
grenades uh or whatever you know okay we
need to make sure that they'll eat the
grenade and then blow up like the reason
we build these scripting level design
tools you know it's it's just it makes
makes it accessible for all the people
on the team if you can't write code to
like put something together try out an
idea um you know see what we can do with
this and the entity system is no
different right a lot of things the
level designers just want to like have
this idea for something that could
happen is that fun look to your own
[Laughter]
salvation yeah I was on TF2 at that time
um and I don't remember exactly I think
it was during 2000 maybe someone else
has probably told you this and got the
dates actually right but at some point
we all jump from TF2 over to Half Life 2
I I feel like that marks the sort of in
some ways in retrospect like the end of
like pre-production really on hlu 2 and
it becomes now like let's build this
thing and ship it
[Music]
actually the first thing I got told to
work on was a jet ski and I spent 3
weeks trying to figure out a jet ski in
first person I was like okay none of
this is working I can't I don't see how
how do you do this without making people
sick so I remember one week and out of
frustration I just made the Airboat um I
don't know maybe it's the Florida bit in
me so Charlie Brown had worked on the
Airboat and then we picked it up a
different group we we started working on
the canals and we had this idea of it
was going to be kind of like a lot of
tricks Under Pressure where you know
you're doing like skateboarding type
moves I think it was Kelly Bailey who
basically said you know I'm I'm playing
the canals and I'm trying to do these
tricks and I'm failing and then I'm
getting shot and uh he's like I want to
be like Smokey in the Bandit I just want
to be smashing my way out we did this
whole other pass of the canals where we
dialed down the consequences for failing
the tricks and we we dialed up the
feeling of you know power some players
absolutely refused to really stay in
their airboats they wanted to get out
and look under every Rock behind every
tree for those players we had to craft
enough density through the lengths of
the canals to keep them entertained and
happy and then there were people who
just wanted to smash through everything
and treat it like a racing s and so the
game had to be fun and interesting for
them and sometimes that would Clash if
you stop here we're going to give you a
reward basically either a narrative
reward or like an actual like in-game
like
reward the Lambda caches the Lambda
signs we used them away a lot more in
the canals and part of that is is
literally because we did it afterwards
like I I mean I'd worked on on Coast
maps and we didn't have that yet you
know the canal are restrictive cuz we
want you to drive this airboat through
them and we've got all these fun things
to do like you could jump over things
you could smash through things the worst
case scenario is you're a trapped with
people who have guns and they're
shooting at you and you you don't
necessarily have a way of shooting back
so you know that led to well we need to
add a weapon to the vehicles well part
of it was the helicopter was such a
persistent pain in your ass that we
really wanted to put a bow on that whole
experience and give you some
vindications some you know Vengeance
where you get to now hunt the helicopter
so as soon as we attach it I one thing
we intentionally really intentionally
did is you start to drive down the
tunnel and the helicopter pops down in
your face and it's blocking you and you
have no choice but to just shoot it if
you want it to go away and then you see
it flee and so it's like oh okay the
players could connect the dots right now
it's my turn uh so the next sequence is
all about chasing the helicopter down to
that final battle at the
dam I remember we worked pretty
intentionally to make it the ultimate
showdown between you and the helicopter
and some of it was by accident I
remember Brian Jacobson who did a lot of
the code for that uh at one point it
accidentally did this thing where it
just spit out a ton of bombs and we were
like that is awesome keep that make that
part of the fight you know we we tried
to make it as action intensive as we
could within reason
right that battle was actually in a way
we designed it to be a final exam we
unraveled those elements into the levels
beforehand right you learned how to
dodge bombs you learned how to shoot at
it and you learned how to shoot while
driving and then we throw those things
together at you with a little bit of a
Twist canals was sort of like a crucible
because a lot of good things came out of
it because it was such a difficult ult
design problem the easy thing to do is
to make a punishing design where you you
just say you can't go here and we're
going to shoot you and force you to fail
and fail and fail until you get to see
the next part of the game it's much
harder to create something where the
player feels there's an evolution they
have some power and some agency so their
skill is being rewarded and they can be
creative in that restrictive environment
you can spin around the boach till you
got a feel for the car when you're done
head for the deal
water so basically had a whole car
engine down through transmission down
into gearing and differentials and
turning the tires but then it turned out
like oh we can really only go 15 20 M an
hour otherwise you would blast through
the extense of the map in about 10
seconds which wasn't going to do anybody
any good people made jumps to made all
these things nothing was working so I
was like oh you must be doing a jump I'm
just going to turn off gravity on the
car for a little while and let it just
go and then gradually ramp it back in so
that it actually felt like you were
jumping it was interesting how like the
Dynamics of the buggy was so much about
like the the perceived experience versus
how it actually like performed it just
sounds like it's going faster than it is
so Jay and I worked really hard on these
engine sounds and this fake transmission
and doing all this stuff but you're
really going like 30 miles an hour maybe
so it's like someone just driving around
in first gear got pulled into Coast one
because I was interested in working on
more game stuff but two it was the
biggest I guess group of people
utilizing the displacement Tech since it
was more of a Terrain thing and Outdoors
and we were trying to figure out how we
wanted to use the displacements meaning
we knew we wanted the things to look
more natural there was a lot more
geometry in those Maps than our previous
ones given just displacements in general
we were always struggling with
performance and trying to figure out how
to make things a little bit faster
easier where we could make things do
what we wanted them to do but not
necessarily cost as much as they they
cost it's much faster than walking speed
so you just signed up for building a
huge amount of game people can just stop
and get out anywhere so now you have
this trade-off of density versus
distance we got a vehicle we want to
drive for a while so make those levels
long but from halflife one we still had
the philosophy of there should be
something cool around every corner not
like a monster popping out of you but
different reasons to be engaged in the
world so they would dot the co Coastline
with little towns and you knew if you
went exploring you'd always get some
kind of reward for that it might be a
health pack and ammo or it might be a
character interaction so that would let
the player set their own pace and feel
like they get to explore the world and
they're always rewarded for that but if
they wanted to drive straight through
they could I worked on like the the area
where there's the the roller mines first
come in and and the you know you're
going along a curving path and then
there's like a they blow up all the the
rocks and drop stuff in front of your
path to try and slow you down and then
you've got like a little house fight
there were cases early on where people
would just try to drive past everything
and like why would I stop at this I've
got a car and so we really wanted them
to like be fairly unavoidable and so
you'd have to get out and deal with
taking them off your car and then you'd
you know be in the space so it's really
fun just you know jumping in there with
the combin soldiers and crafting little
fight scenarios what makes AI fights
interesting is not that they're the
smartest or the best or anything like
it's easy to make AI that can just
perfectly shoot the player and kill them
that's not what makes them smart it's
putting on a show that makes them feel
interesting so like in in that fight in
particular you go up inside of a
building and you get to the second floor
and you're fighting guys in there and
they kind of pull you up there there's
guys up in there and as you go up and
fight them that happens but then more
guys spawn outside like there's a bunch
of Windows up in that top section and
and there's a crate sort of near the
window and when you go over to get that
crate they start shooting through the
window at you and it's not that the AI
actually knows that you're there and
starts shooting at the window the moment
they see you there's actually um we have
these things called um bulls eyes that
you could place in spots and they
basically would act like a Target that
the AI wanted to shoot you know a lot of
that isn't actually the AI being you
know doing this carefully crafted thing
it's it's more of us thinking like what
makes this like a neat presentation for
the player and gives them that sense
that they're kind of they need to hunker
down like later on in the same Coastline
there's a sequence where you're fighting
a gunship and you're in the the um
Lighthouse and as you go up the
lighthouse it's like sort of predicting
where you are and shooting through the
windows right in front of you and giving
you that same sort of show and that's
all like Bull's eyes and things almost
every game you play you you're
developing a sense of Mastery and that
actual sense of progress and Mastery is
is the fun piecing it all together is
like very core to what makes it
fun hello Dr Freeman the car's all ready
for
you hop in and I'll lower you down to
the
beach we did the P driveable crane first
I think right and then we pul and then
we went back and used it again you know
at the start tutorial like it's perfect
training you're going to this is how
that thing works don't forget cuz it's
about to happen later you have to do it
we did actually get um very close to the
base of a crane you know obviously you
want to be in the crane you want to be
driving it all the these things but yeah
we did get up very close to this crane
again I think it was asking somebody
we're just um wanting to take some
pictures for a video game could you just
let us in try to act as like nice and
non-threatening as possible we need the
buggy to get into a state where it was
flipped so you could have to learn to to
recover and all that stuff like oh we're
going to flip it over and then you have
to to proceed you have to use the the
gravity gun we're just trying to wrap
that in some sort of narrative instead
of just spitting some text that tells
you with this happens you know that was
you know I mean the crane was a hard
physics problem cuz like one of the
worst case scenarios for physics is
really you know high mass objects moving
around cuz they're going to apply an
enormous amount of force to anything
they touch and we have a rigid body
physic system so in the real world when
giant heavy Mass touches something
usually it crushes them we can't really
crush anything so already we're in like
a tricky place the good news was we had
a fixed space it could operate right you
can't we could control how far you could
extend the thing and so as the level
designers could look at and be like
these are the only things that the crane
will ever really be able to interact
with and so we could be pretty careful
around right what are the things that um
that this magnet is going to touch and
let's make sure that at least the
physics works pretty well for
[Music]
that so I worked on the bridge uh as one
of the really early things I worked on
there which was great Sawyer had already
built the bridge it's actually based on
Deception Pass so it's Deception Pass is
nearby here in uh Washington
coincidentally I actually proposed to my
wife there but anyway it's this really
nice bridge that like if you go there
you'll be like oh yeah this is the
halflife 2 Bridge the the fight against
the gunship and everything wasn't really
all put together it was definitely had
that like scary you know fear of heights
scenario of going under the bridge but
we hadn't fully fleshed it all out yet
one of the first things I did was like
What if this was a train bridge and you
had to do this you know play chicken
against the train and getting the timing
quite right was was took a little bit of
of work but hearing the like train horn
come in and the moment of realization
that players would have of like probably
some people die a lot of people probably
die the first time there but you have
this like do I go faster or do I turn
around like what do I do I don't know it
just a it was a fun moment to create all
credit diser on coming up with the going
underneath the bridge scenario people to
this day still are like that freak them
the hell out like a lot of people would
just it's sort of seared in their memory
which is just you know it's what we want
to do when we're creating levels trying
to like capture the sense of height and
playing with the ambient sounds to get
the you know just to capture the sense
of being precarious and uh high above
the ground was a it was just a fun
little design challenge David came up
with that and we play tested it and the
first time it play tested I think the
person who was play testing their
knuckles were white and it was really
tense and of course then someone had the
brilliant eye idea of like oh they
finally made it they felt great now
we're going to make them go back oh and
the gunship yeah that came in yeah so
that was that was always
fun there's this thing we call Edge
friction so when you're moving you have
a friction that just reduces your normal
movement rate by an amount but what we
would do is whenever players would get
close to edges we would increase that
friction a lot so that people wouldn't
accidentally fall off things it's just
not fun for the player right um so there
was definitely a bit of friction play
involved
[Music]
there Gordon
Freeman hurry get in the basement we're
expecting gunships at any moment he
became iconic for reasons I don't
totally understand except the
performance we were calling that town
little new Little Odessa or little old
new Odessa and then I got spam email
from Odessa cubbage or something like
that it was definitely a name that came
out of an email spam and I'm like this
name is amazing so it went straight into
the game and then John Lowry came in and
acted him with his fake British accent
damn let me just send a warning to
Lighthouse Point and then I'll come
right up and lend a hand so Desa cubage
had this whole problem of like training
the rocket launcher that was a real pain
the laser guiding aspect was just a
nightmare to train cuz uh training in
combat's always a nightmare by itself
cuz people are under under Jess trying
not to die they're focusing on some
other thing that's threatening them it's
hard to observe what's going on
rationally and draw lessons from it
cleanly um so you always know it's going
to be hard if you're trying to teach
something you can trying to teach in
combat we watch a play test you know
they step out and they fire a rocket at
the gunship and then they duck behind
cover so the laser do goes onto the onto
the fence in front of him we all hear
the rocket turn around and start back
and so basically here we go louder and
then the player looks out again at the
gunship and the rocket go like loops
around back at the great God chip and
we're like oh and then he Ducks back
again and we're like oh my God we hear
the rocket getting louder and louder and
he peeks out again it whips off again an
integrated part that I think has really
always been important something that
Gabe introduced in halflife one was the
way that we play test and then iterate
really rapidly on the play test results
so you have
dozens and dozens of people come through
one section of the game and you sit
there painfully silently taking notes
while they struggle and get frustrated
and totally misunderstand your brilliant
design um and then you go and you you
fix that over and over and over again if
your title is game designer and your
design sucks then it can be threatening
right like maybe I'm bad at my job and I
should get fired right and so a lot of
the games industry never did did any
testing at all with this play testing
process that that's what basically
taught me design in a lot of ways we
would just you know we'd come up with an
idea for the helicopter and then we'd be
like okay let's put it in front of
somebody and watch it happen and then
we'd very quickly start realizing that
our mental model of like how people are
reacting to this stuff is wildly
different than what we
expected I joined the team in January
2000 I had met Gabe when he was starting
valve and I was at sier online but
pretty much the first thing was you know
Gabe was like so when you're at Sierra
we did this deal with you for halflife
and halflife too you need to go fix that
cuz we don't like the deal that we did
you know the intellectual property for
halflife was owned by vendi uh the Team
Fortress IP was owned by vendi so was
get back our P get a better royalty rate
and then um have the ability to
experiment with online distribution we
knew we were going to grow the team and
then part of the deal was also that we
were going to take on all of the funding
responsibility for halflife2 TF2 all
those things there was cash flow from
halflife we figuring out how to do
things here and there like expansion
packs uh a large part of was Gabe
tapping
into his assets uh he had done fairly
well at Microsoft not crazy well but
things started to get a little
[Laughter]
thin so I assume you guys have talked
to Scott or Eric or something about sort
of the context of the whole yes we
talked to Scott Eric and G a
b Sierra by that point had become
acquired by vendi had worldwide
distribution rights uh but only for
retail package product vendi was
licensing Counterstrike to cyber cafes
we went to vendy and said hey this is
not a big deal just just agree that this
is outside of your license and you know
we've spent a little bit on attorney's
fees just cover you know some tens of
thousand thousands just covers for that
and we'll move on and just keep going
and and they wouldn't do it I think some
people at vendi did not like the New
Deal that they ended up signing and I
think there there were some hurt
feelings in some quarters about that
deal when we said hey the cyber cafe
thing you know you really can't do that
coming on top of you know a year
negotiations and torturous negotiations
I think that just struck an angry chord
we ended up filing the lawsuit but
really just on on this narrow thing of
like hey Court you know will you go just
read this language and say are they
outside the license or
not uh and vendi decided to go World War
II you filed our case in Seattle federal
court in Seattle and they hired Law Firm
to defend it of course there was some
IAL skirmishing about uh Discovery there
were some disputes and motions that had
to be decided by the judge and those
went all valves way and then suddenly uh
that the law firm disappeared they hired
a you know a big scary Law Firm from San
Francisco they thought okay you know
valves had some success in this case and
so we need to change their mindset from
we think we're going to be successful to
we're going to be destroyed uh the next
thing we knew here comes a this big
stack of counter claims everything from
cancelling the 2001 agreement to
obtaining ownership of all the half-life
IP to keeping us from doing steam to you
name it where they included Scott and
Julie Lynch and Gabe and Lisa Newell his
wife at that time personally as
defendants and so it was kind of like
well we're going to put valve out of
business and then we're going to
bankrupt the two of you
that I think that was a lot of what they
felt like was their path towards winning
this fight they decided that it would
have more effect and be scarier if
process server showed up at everybody's
house in the night and hand I mean
so yeah a real [__] move it's not a
legal strategy it's a basically trying
to intimidate you in other words they're
saying not only are we going to take all
this money from the company but we're
going to take money from you personally
as
well I can't think of another case when
that happened they were certainly a lot
bigger than we were vendi was a
multinational conglomerate as compared
to us their funding was infinite it felt
very David versus cath Publishers at
that time in the industry were used to
being able to bully developers right and
so this was really about an assertion of
power as much as it was optimizing for a
financial outcome the tactics that they
were using were trying to just run us
out of money right so they knew how much
money we were making because they were
doing retail distribution of our games
and so they were just trying to crank up
our legal costs as just another way of
draining resources from the company we
were protected from that a lot
internally so we didn't have to think
about it they did a pretty good job of
letting the team concentrate on what the
team could do without worrying about the
future of the company so much I me that
was my perspective so yeah I definitely
was not shielded from that the lawsuit
was something where it's like created
all this uncertainty around whether the
game's going to come out vendy was
definitely trying to use that as
leverage uh and so even if we finish the
game they're not going to let us release
it there came a point where um gab
pretty much used up his liquid assets
and he was like you know should I put
the house on the market and I was like
yeah I think it's the time where you put
the house in the market if if we want to
keep going the company was pretty close
to bankrupt I was pretty close to going
personally bankrupt we we went all in
it's like there was no money left like
how how anxious was that for you
personally I I don't know
uh there's certain things that I just
I'm kind of a weird person in a number
of Dimensions like I don't really think
oh this is super scary like I don't have
an emotional response to it I just say
well this is this is what we're doing
this is how and you know we'll see how
it how it plays out so I don't think it
was super stressful to me right I mean
it it didn't really bother me like I was
diving in South Africa recently and a
shark tried to bite me a couple of times
and the people around me were way more
freaked out than I was I was like oh a
shark's trying to bite me I should get
away from the shark whereas other people
were having like oh a shark it's trying
to bite somebody you know um and I just
think that's how I'm wired I don't think
it's I don't think it's anything that
speaks to my character or anything at
this like I just seem to not get
particularly agitated around risk
which probably means I take on more risk
than at times than most sane people
would which can be a positive or you can
you can wreck a bunch of other people's
lives being in the neighborhood of your
risk indifference
[Laughter]
[Music]
they're this rigidly structured you know
organization of course they're going to
have this really tur language for
everything they do you know there's sort
of an announcer voice in that that
follows you around and kind of comments
status essentially like how alert the
world is to
you unit
contained I sat down and and just
basically wrote a language for that so
that the soldiers and the metrocops
would have jargon that they would use
then I just used that to kind of encode
so that's where like anticitizen one and
things like that came from rather than
saying the guy with the orange suit is
causing trouble um you know it would be
you know anticitizen one breach scalpel
something sector something so I
basically just had this this little
dictionary then I overdid it on the
vocal processing because they're all
wearing these you know these masks and I
wanted it to sound like they're in a
mask and it was very deliberate to never
have to like shoot somebody that you can
see their face and like we didn't want
you killing humans I mean the metrocops
are humans but we covered all the faces
up I think it was all part of this
calculated and deliberate way of saying
like look games don't just have to be a
certain way there's so much room and
what we can do
here well the the Metro Police and the
combined soldiers share a lot of AI uh
and so there's an internal communication
among them and one of the things we did
both for the sake of difficulty and
Exposition was limit the number of squad
members that could be firing at the
player at any given time I think it's
two so if you have a squad of four a guy
who has an opportunity to shoot at the
player grabs one of those slots uh if
it's available and starts to shoot and
if someone else another Squad member
wants to attack the player but no slots
are available they have to find the next
best thing to do which is I'll get out
of the scene for a second or I'll go
reload or I'll throw a grenade and that
was all stuff that we learned uh
building halflife one and I think got a
lot better
at Half Life 2 used a node graph system
you know hand Place nodes by developers
in the levels would describe a really
super low um Fidelity version of the
environment for the AI to use it enabled
the level designers to sort of inject
and Puppeteer a little bit the AIS in in
ways that were just easier for them to
sort of be in control as opposed to
having to to grab an animator or a
programmer to be able to get really cool
things into the
[Music]
game Flor is lava is like like a really
obvious piece of gameplay uh physics is
really fun to manipulate we just thought
like hey you know you could build your
own path you know we we'd already seen
players who enjoyed moving stuff around
like Building Bridges and stuff and like
we don't have enough moments where like
I just pick up a plank and lay it across
a gap and walk across it like obvious
stuff we we've barely done that in the
whole game and the fact that you're
you're laying stuff down on the floor
means that the Finesse required to do
like precise placement it wasn't
necessary right you're like I just want
to place it here and doesn't matter the
orientation you just kind of jump on it
you do the next one and so on right and
also like training was free like we
didn't have to train it was
like like oh it's finest of his
generation couldn't figure that one out
he tells you exactly how to do it
someone's coming you there stop where
you are stay on the Rocks Don't Step on
the sand it makes the at Lions crazy llo
don't move no help
dear God poor
llo the finest mind of his generation to
come to such an
end we were heading for the vortigon
camp hoping to pick up some bug baits of
these damn things that leave us alone
without
llo what's the point you just give these
NPCs a name at the moment they die and
let the fans fill in their whole life
story and give give them something to
play with the free man will have need of
these fots on the paths ahead gather
them now Nova Prospect and the ant lions
with the pheromone balls were uh really
fun because it let you experience them
in a different way and it was another
classic example of getting the most
value out of Technology Investments that
people could I remember the beach thing
the design intention was definitely to
make it feel like a a sort of D-Day
Beach Landing um you didn't come from
the water but but you're storming up
towards these old gun placements if I
remember right with combine in them and
you're like invading the bunkers and
you're bringing your horde with you
you're you're overwhelming the defense
these in place defenses it was
surprising how much chaos you could get
away with like we I remember we did a
lot of tuning to make sure the the ant
line spawn we had difficulties from time
to time with like design some choke
point or challenge or whatever in the
antline flow rate wasn't enough to make
it feel um chaotic enough like we had a
we had a an atmospheric goal too it
wasn't just about like mechanically can
you overcome this you wanted to feel
like your forces have stormed the walls
they're everywhere there's chaos all
around you and so a lot of the tuning
was about uh achieving that feeling not
just about mechanically getting past the
enemies that we'd set NOA Prospect was
different than a lot of the maps that I
worked on at least is that in that we
had some early art prototypes that were
done we have this whole concept of like
Zoo Maps we call them which are
basically like little art test scenes uh
how they would fit together and some
basic lighting but by the time alab got
to NOA Prospect we knew we were coming
in with ant lines and with bug bait and
so we already knew that a bunch of stuff
was going to change because we had to uh
support you know you and your army of
ant lines fighting combine soldiers ant
lines look great whenever they were
being shot by anyone like like particle
Flex flying off and you know they just
did they always like great and so
setting them up against com soldiers
looked great setting up against pets
looked great those were super fun
scenarios to work on though because
having these ant lines that you could
just use in any way you wanted was
really fun like and coming from the
coast like just the contrast of like
shrinking everything down and then just
piling it full of stuff was was a lot of
fun the first time I saw one of those it
was I think it was Ted's Ted Bachman's
concept I just thought I can't believe
that I get to use a creature this cool
in in level design like these these guys
are really really really fun to use I
remember Kelly Bailey had uh created a
short list things like he wanted
flocking flyers and he wanted a a moving
guard Tower which was the first
description of the Strider was a mobile
guard Tower so I saw that and
immediately understood that you know
kind of orchestrating the enemies in
that way trying to get the most variety
and the most breadth of uh shape and mve
and uh experience was the correct way to
move forward the design for that first
Strider map was something I came up with
and I was really passionate about it was
all about like running across and just
getting like one shot in your tush right
just as you made it through even just
hearing the the sound the Thump Thump
Thump of them walking like you know okay
there's there's like a boss nearby you
just see the legs walking by but you
can't see the body like there are so
many things you can do with these guys
honestly there were still people on the
team I think that were still thinking
that we were gonna bomb that was that
people are just going to not be
impressed when did you know it was going
to be good E3 yep E3 yeah I'd say the
same
thing yeah it seems like at some point
there was an E3 de demo that we got
together that we didn't end up showing
but at least at that point it just felt
like oh wow we actually we actually have
made something here we you know we went
through and made a bunch of demos for
2002 and everybody looked at them and
it's
like we're still not confident about
this and we don't think we've hit the
bar so we're not going to we're not
going to go at all like they had totally
planned to go and then when 2003 rolled
around I just remember everyone was
still terrified we're like okay how are
we going to craft everything we've had
into like a number of messages about
what this product is and like you came
up with like The Core theme of each one
of these movies oh do be careful we
didn't really understand at the time I
think the embarrassment of riches that
we had um we looked at it from two
angles one was a set of technical
features um a sort of conceptual listing
of things that we thought were important
you know like physics and things like
that and and then the other side was uh
content-based what areas of the game
were Innovative what areas of the story
we thought were compelling which
characters we thought were worth people
paying attention to and so it was an
interesting sort of of uh which features
and which content are the best showcase
for for all those things a lot of what
was in the demos was rendering
technology but I think the stuff that
felt the strongest to most of us at the
time was really physics
based so something looks like wood then
it sounds like wood scrapes like wood
floats like it and if you shoot it it'll
fragment like wood
to people at that time it was pretty
mind-blowing just to watch thing be able
to pick things up knock other things
over use things in a way that felt uh
true to a three-dimensional reality
maybe it's on those videos I don't
remember but people were gasping and you
know hitting the people next to them
because they couldn't really believe
what they were seeing on the
screen there's no limitation on the
complexity of those interactions
so it's this level of believable and
consistent interactivity that opens the
door to a wide variety of new gameplay
mechanics I'm this will run on my
486 you know that person who was talking
about a 486 like it obviously it's just
about like that you must have a
supercomputer behind like how are you
how are you even doing this what what is
going on
[Music]
the lines outside the booth became
enormous and it was the thing that it
really distorted the rest of e3 because
so many people were anxious to come see
our demo and I remember seeing this
absolutely enormous line with like some
pretty well-known people in there right
mamoto was in line for this stuff and
like will right I think yeah will right
there was a bunch and so then like yeah
after that was all done like people on
the team were just like okay we are we
are ready we can ship this game we know
uh we know we've got something good it
was really easy at that point like it
felt like we were rolling the ball
downhill after until it leaked until it
[Music]
leaked when something like this happens
there's not like a big sign saying
you've been hacked and somebody has like
you start off with something that just
doesn't make a whole lot of sense and
you start pulling on that sweater thread
gab's brother had a company called
tangis and they made wearable computer
stuff so he was kind of winding it down
and he had one or two Unix servers that
hosted the tes.com domain name
Unfortunately they were put inside the
firewall and didn't have the latest
Linux or whatever security updates on
them and so this kid from Germany was
able to sort of exploit his way into
that he sat there for months I think he
was able to sync the build all the code
I was riffing ideas for I think in
particular Counterstrike that
information ended up on one of the
internet chat rooms and I only two
people knew the contents of that email
of course gave it myself and I went to
itg and said this could only have come
from a leaked email uh we got to figure
out how that got out there but I
remember at some point Gabe walking
around you know like one of those Moment
Like turn your computer off something
just happened like I remember video my
desk and coming like turn your computer
off I think we're being hacked and I was
what like I didn't know what to do I I
actually did not know what to do I I
remember coming in that morning and
figuring it out and it just felt like
someone had just punched me in the gut
you know it's like the bid in movies
where like after an explosion they'll
have a scene where someone's like
stagging around the street and
everyone's like yeah uh what's this mean
like can we still keep working on the
game like is someone just going to
release the whole game tomorrow and I
don't know if the guy who hacked it
intended I think yeah he show it
intended the wide distribution he showed
it to friends and then one of his
friends posted it somewhere yeah uh
unfortunate
[Music]
yeah and one of the things I think
that's pretty interesting is how much
the leak of the game the the hack of our
Network and the leak of the game how
much that kind of shattered that
confidence it was like you know having a
movie that you're working on be spoiled
for the world that's how it felt because
we knew it would be hard for people to
know that that existed and not go look
at it all it looked all broken to us and
it just felt really demoralizing oh man
I was seriously affected by that I yeah
I was I was pretty angry so I don't know
it kind of affected me for a while you
know having it be having it called the
beta when it was not even close to being
a beta work in progress you know wasn't
really ready to be seen yet normally the
office is pretty vibrant and loud and
people riding scooters in the hallway
and doing all sorts of stuff gabes tub
and throat singing and they got very
still and very quiet I remember that
that was very eerie that was the game
that was going to make or break the
company we didn't know if we were going
to have to go find jobs not only did it
show everybody that we were not anywhere
near we where we said we would be but
all the work that we had in progress all
the plans that we were making were just
laid out be and so a lot of us just
thought oh we're toast we've worked so
hard are we can go bankrupt and then all
that while Scott Lynch and Gabe were
being sued by Sierra their you know
wives being delivered subpoenas and so
it was this super dark uh time so there
were two interesting threads going on
one was you know traditional law
enforcement intelligence agencies and
they were doing their thing and issuing
subpoenas and seizing devices and then
we asked our community to help us out
and I think GBE started to realize that
he you know he was being tracked down by
the community right everything was being
essentially it was an open- sourced
investigation so you could see that they
were getting closer and that's when he
reached out to me of course I was
insanely furious with him but we ended
up running this sort of scheme with him
where I was like oh wow you must be
really good at security issues we should
have you come out an interview and the
FBI was going to arrest him when he got
off the plane and then the apparently
the German police sweep in right as he's
about to to leave because it turns out
he's also guilty of a bunch of bank
fraud and bank hacking and all that he
haed a bunch of huge huge companies over
there as well and so they were already
well aware of him how much it harmed us
financially or like how much the the
success of the game was harmed by that
very debatable you know so it was hard
for us to go through internally but uh
in the end I wouldn't have wanted to
have it be a whole like law enforcement
debacle after that it just yeah it
wouldn't have really helped anyone and
say we should never be laxed about
security but like if we could survive
that like maybe you know we'll survive
anything because at the end of the day
the Special Sauce was everything that
happened between the moment of that leak
and when we actually shipped and if you
look at that version of the game it's
just so so not what the final game ended
up being and so even if our competition
had all the source code and that
executable they're still not able to
produce half life to from it because the
company kept moving forward and the
company was the interesting Special
Sauce
[Music]
Gabe in particular he had kind of a
pencil sketch of an idea in his head of
what would become steam but it was clear
that Team Fortress classic and then
later Counterstrike it was it was
fundamentally the thing that we were
really attracted to was our ability to
ship content directly to our customers I
mean there was a set of uh business
goals that ended up being part of steam
but fundamentally there was it was a a
bunch of game development goals that it
was servicing that were so attractive to
us it was a very weird time like I don't
think people understand how many times
we would go to people and say no you
will be able to distribute software over
the internet and have people just say no
you never it will never happen I'm not
talking about one or two people I mean
like 99% of the companies we talked to
said it will never happen your retail
Salesforce will never let it happen but
also people would say users aren't going
to want this right people want physical
copy like there were so many bad faith
arguments that were being made real tale
sales is not the goal right it's
actually an impediment that it's it's
somebody who sits between you and the
customer and we ended up going out to
the finding this company called applied
Microsystems so we ended up hiring most
of the original steam team from that
other company to build initially this
sort of in-game advertising streaming
model but then there was the Epiphany
that hey it's just bits why don't we
just download whole games this way you
guys go off and do it the decision to
not only use steam to ship halflife 2
but actually to require steam even in
the versions that were purchased at
retail in a box was the most interesting
decision of of all those because it it
turned out to be an incredibly important
decision for the future of the company
and a lot of us were nervous and a lot
of the people who had been at valve for
a long time since the very beginning
were the most nervous about that
decision and so it was one of the rare
exceptions to our decision-making
process usually and Gabe had to really
step in and say no actually we're we're
doing it this way
I remember coming to work in the morning
working at half 2 which meant that you
know by the time you you go home at
night me being 24 a 24 year old idiot
all I wanted to do was keep working on
the game and you know I started just
making the game work on multiplayer
right you know mostly just working on
prediction like what would it feel like
to have a gravity gun on a multiplayer
setting right getting physics objects to
work and it was just C curiosity Scott
Dalton saw me working on it and he's
like I'll make a map and then we play
put the map up we started playing in the
office in between you know builds of
half lifee 2 like play test and I
remember Gabe walking by my desk and was
him going like what's that and I said oh
it's halflife multiplayer and he's like
show it to me tomorrow and he just
walked away I think that is one of the
advantages of the general cost we always
pay uh to keep our code in a single code
base so when we're working on TF2 and
half 2 at the same time at that point
we're paying this continuous cost in
halflife 2 for the fact that it's built
upon an engine that's designed to do
multiplayer but it means that when you
get to this later point where you start
asking well can we build multiplayer
Deathmatch out of this like the code's
all sort of built upon a fundamentally a
client server sort of
foundation definitely the most
entertaining thing that you could throw
at somebody that happened to be
scattered around the world was picking
up a toilet and hurling it at someone's
head and then having that show up in the
upper right corner of your screen with
name toilet name uh was uh very
satisfying I was also selfishly trying
to get the game ported to multiplayer so
then we can release the tools the SDK
ready to go like even me like modm
makers could just immediately start
making multiplayer game uh mods rather
than waiting for us to do it or someone
else to pick it up
we were so heads down working on what we
were working on we didn't really get a
chance to play the train station I
remember that that was one of the
lessons that came away from halflife one
is like we need to be building these
games backwards in a sense the first
thing we're going to put in front of
people is the thing we built when we're
as good as we can be at it you know we
know our tools and things like that and
a lot of the anxiety over are we
building a good game was behind us and I
felt really confident yeah we're
building a really good game
[Music]
we are entering the guard
do this this train train station is very
important because it's one of the main
Inspirations for the train station of
City 17 where the player starts the
reason why I'm using a Parisian station
produced by Eiffel who did the Eiffel
Tower is that there's an identical
station in Budapest train station is the
last bit we worked on right and you we
always want to build the start of the
game late as as late as we can cuz we
understand our game at that point uh in
general the train station was a really
interesting problem because it was
basically one big Coro sequence intended
deliver atmosphere and story and
background and sort of set your
expectations for the world we let the
designers who were really good at this
stuff figure out what was a good
experience and then we were kind of
always there to provide dialogue acting
stuff like this guy I think it was
pretty clear too that we wanted to Pro
provide incentive to the player at this
point uh about how people were being
mistreated about how bad the situation
was here and um kind of start to trigger
that righteous indignation early all
this stuff is fun to look at you just
assume it doesn't move and you can't
interact with it you can't pick it up
because all the stuff we're going to do
late with the gravity gun and everything
like first we got to start just mundane
stuff like like that food you know that
little empty bit of food I mean it
happens like the moment you leave the
train wind comes and blows all the trash
away you can see the v s so like guy
pushing on the cases on all those things
fall off pick those up and we're like if
it if it doesn't have to be bolted down
just make sure it gets knocked over
citizen come with me this guy looks
Vaguely
Familiar something about the way he
walks way he it's like a Beer
Drinker who would have thought Barney
has the capacity to go undercover right
like that that is that seemed to be you
know above his payg grade above his
intelligence play pay grade from the
get-go look at that beautiful animation
but where does hack go it's
gone something is right here magical
combine we were trying to figure out how
to get people to figure out how to pick
up things and do things and we were all
just sitting around cuz we've been
having this problem for weeks racking
our brains and I think Robin had a coat
can on his desk and at some point I got
frustrated I smacked it off his desk I'm
like well you pick that up then and
everyone kind of sat around was
like I just found it just an immensely
satisfying piece of like storytelling
and World setting you we got to use our
physics tools and the Coro tools and all
of those things Blended together into
this very simple clean moment like that
can cup is perfect also because while
it's teaching you how to manipulate
objects it's also telling you something
about the com by themselves in the Metro
cops your relationship yeah so like it
was a twofer right we got those two at
the same time physics is going to be a
big part of our game by the time you
left train station as a as a player like
you understood that and you come to
appreciate it yeah cuz we couldn't wait
until you got the Raven home before you
found out how awesome physics it is if
you'd had any kind of weapon I think
they would have had to kill you and we
found the longer we sort of held that
away from ourselves the more we were
forced to come up with stuff that was
still entertaining that you could do
like like the raid is a whole you know
in the tournament is a whole thing that
could work because the player could only
run we don't very often Force the player
into a very specific set of actions um
that's one of the few times that we had
to learn to really Corral the player and
I think we ended ended up being pretty
successful like I think the consequences
for sort of not following on the clear
path were quick and
efficient get in here quick keep moving
the roof so when you build the world I
start with the infrastructure what's
really interesting for me is what it's
not visible to the tourist which is the
courtyard the backyard uh the shafts and
the smoke stacks and the wires and every
city has this whole uh
existence and you know people are
usually blind to it and they we tend to
look at store fronts right yeah I mean a
lot of it came down art Direction I mean
Victor was very very familiar with all
that the look and feel you know there
was certain patterns and certain um yeah
iconic shapes that anybody who lived
there could could pick up on you know
they're like oh yeah my grandmother had
that dresser or whatever and my my
parents are from Argentina and to they
have that kind of sensibility but a lot
of it came down to the the reference
Gathering which was from Bulgaria from
Paris we have these buildings that again
have a back Courtyards they have big
staircases uh they have Sellar Spa uh
atic spaces Sellar spaces and the
apartments have big windows and thick
walls so this was providing already a
lot of context for people who can hide
in these apartments help me stop we
didn't do
anything they'll be looking for you now
you'd better run I remember that we
wanted to have the player see proof that
the combine were evil people not that
they were gray in any way that they were
objectively the bad guys uh and then we
had it to where you go upstairs and then
we really carefully and intentionally
frame fr the reveal of the world to
where you see the Citadel front and
center and it's clearly in an alert
State the four of us the city 17 cabal
we' done City 17 which is a bunch of
hard problems we've done U Raven home
which is a different set of hard
problems we were like I don't know four
months from trying to lock down the game
or something I it was really late I may
have the dates wrong but it was really
late and there was a bunch of gameplay
that that was in there that hadn't
really received a lot of like
development we were coming from working
with pretty much every tool in the game
in c17 to going back to basically you
have a pistol and Metro cops not much
really so John and I John guthy and I
absolutely love exploding barrels so we
just used them absolutely everywhere we
could we set them up we Lov ragd doll
magnets and physics it's just one of my
favorite tools it's basically you have a
point in space that when a character
dies they turn into a ragd doll and then
you have a ragd doll magnet that says
okay if there is a if there is a any
ragd doll in this radius pull towards me
and then you can give it a strength and
so if somebody dies in an especially
dramatic location you can have an
especially dramatic death um and we just
use that absolutely everywhere I mean
you can use it to just pull someone
directly down so in that bridge the the
train bridge I put magnets directly
beneath their feet so it looks like they
just like the planks beneath their feet
broke and they just fell directly down
Ian they died from a broken plank which
doesn't make any sense but they looked
pretty cool it was so orchestrated I
guess because we didn't want it to like
we didn't really have a lot of time to
have like a lot of bugs come out of
it you our team was the one that did the
Citadel you know how I said that there
was multiple passes on the product over
the course of the thing well Citadel had
almost no pass and we were think think
about Street war and we were like well
we just had like this incredibly intense
you know Strider fight how are we going
to outdo that especially when we only
got a a month to do this thing we then
came up with the idea of like well what
if we made this just be your God and
this is the reward you've won the game
enjoy we're going to like break all the
rules and let you let you be God for a
little bit picking up you know the
enemies as as ragd dolls and throwing
them around really came out of that
development tool because you could pick
them up and and and move them around and
people are like I don't know that's
pretty fun why don't why can't we do
that in the game it was either a week or
a day it was incredibly quick uh I had
every single mechanic of the Citadel
mocked up uh the combine ball was
actually a very very heavy watermelon
that would bounce around and eventually
break up I had spikes in the wall that
you could skewer them on we had electric
fields that you can throw them in uh we
had the zero g fields that they could
that they would get stuck in and we had
ripping off the machines off the walls
all that stuff all came together Within
in an incredibly short period of time
just a day a couple days very shortly
after that people were like H you know
we're having a real hard time with the
ar2 all fire so maybe we'll just steal
this because it's kind of cool and we'll
bring it earlier in the game game
development never does this it never
like just materializes out of nothing in
that short a time and is just something
everybody's excited and happy about and
it just uh it felt really it felt really
good to be a part of that
[Laughter]
I started working on trying to find
another source of funding to keep valve
going I started working on a deal with a
big publisher that was for Counterstrike
2 so we're right there uh ready to sign
we're really kind of running on fumes at
that point and then get a phone call and
they're like yeah we changed our mind
we're not doing the deal you know there
I remember one conversation with Gabe
which is like he was like so how [__]
are we uh and I was like well we're yeah
we're kind of screwed we could probably
reformat everything that we're doing but
it means we'd lay off people and we
still had the huge uncertainty of what
is going to happen in the lawsuit
immediately started chasing another
publisher and uh were able to get a deal
done with another publisher for
Counterstrike 2 when we got the deal
done Gabe at that point was super into
knives and as the deal gift for the
parties he uh built a knife that was
inscribed Counter-Strike 2 and so the
deal structure was after we ship
halflife 2 if you decide that you don't
want to keep moving forward then you can
just decide to terminate the deal and
we'll pay the money back that ended up
happening so maybe a good choice because
it took us a long time to ship
Counterstrike too so that that we got
done in in probably May of 2003 and then
through some more
depositions uh theendi figured out that
we had gotten this new infusion of
capital and kind of lost their mind
trying to figure out how did that happen
because it was clearly part of their
strategy was you know running us out of
money but what we decided was hey let's
focus on the real nub of this and the
thing that's going to lead to a
resolution getting the judge to decide
that we were right about the cyber cafe
business and also to decide that we were
right that if you were Distributing
these properties without a license that
that's copyright infringement you know
we had asked for information about what
they were doing in Asia including Korea
and they I think to try to make our
lives more difficult produce a big chunk
of documents in Korean that were in
Korean I mean everything from email to
contracts to you you name it and one of
the things they were doing is just
dumping huge amounts of Discovery on it
to force us to to go and just have
somebody go and look through it it's
like oh look they ordered sandwiches
again right it has nothing to do with
the lawsuit it's just an attempt to
overwhelm us with tens of millions of
pages of documents on the assumption
that uh there's nothing in it that will
be particularly problematic for their
case that will eventually just give will
either spend a bunch of money which
plays into their hands or we'll just
eventually give up because it's finding
a needle in the Hy stck uh and then we
found the needle in the Hast stack and
and that changed things quite
dramatically it just so happened that
there was an intern summer associate who
was a native Korean speaker and I said
Andrew hey can you look at this pile
here and just can you just tell me what
what's in there I would guess that that
particular insurent probably went
through a couple thousand documents that
day and only one was consequential and
then and they they said well there's
these other emails between these vice
presidents where one says something like
hey we destroyed those valve documents
like you
asked and then I said uh are you sure it
says that and uh I said yeah that's
that's what it says and so of course
that led to a conversation between me
and the lawyer for their side about hey
it looks like your guys are destroying
evidence what's up with that they wrote
back and said you're out of your mind
whoever translated doesn't know what
they're talking about and I talked to
Andrew again I said well looks like
we're going to have a kind of a fight
about this are you uh we're going to
need an affidavit from you about your
translation can you tell me a little bit
about your Korean skills he goes well
I'm a native speaker at UCLA I majored
in Korean language studies
and I said that's good that sounds like
we're in good shape the assistant
general manager in Korea sending the
letter to the general manager of Korea
saying I have destroyed those documents
related to the valve case as directed
which I think is one of Carl's happiest
moments as a lawyer in his entire career
just like stuff like this never ever
happens I did a lot of losses for a long
time I never saw anything like that
never maybe there was document
destruction that
couldn't be proved but that was like
we're talking about it in writing I'd
never I'd never seen that before at that
point judge zilly said all matters of
fact are now according to valve you know
you don't get to contest any of those uh
now we're just discussing uh the settle
you know how much you're going to have
to pay and what the damages are and Gabe
was still pretty mad he was mad he he
really didn't want to settle he he was
mad enough that he wanted to keep going
but I remember sitting down with Carl uh
and having a conversation with Carl and
I was like so Carl what do you think
should should we settle at this point is
the right number and he was like well
you know there's this old saying there's
a difference between being a pig and a
hog Carl was done with the deposition
and that was the only question I asked
him to ask that particular witness was
is halflife 2 being replicated and
shipped to retailers he said yes and
that the relief was hey no matter what
at least the game's going to get out to
people which is kind of a uh that's
pretty unusual way to find out from your
publisher that uh they're shipping your
game to retail
[Music]
you know I kind of been thinking about
this for the last few days and you know
what if there was one thing that I can
point to that made us successful over
over that uh development period And I
think that it was really this culture
that Gabe created where we were hiring
people that were senior enough to be
managers but also passionate enough to
still be individual contributors uh they
were willing to stake their credibility
and their name on these big features and
sometimes spend years working on those
features yeah and it was like you know 6
7even days a week you know 10 to 14
hours a day it it wasn't always I would
say a good 18 months at least but a lot
of good memories though I mean stay
everyone in that room has such a great
sense of humor like we we all we KN we
knew each other's sense of humor we
trusted each other we respected each
other enough that like we could we could
rib each other without you know like
stepping on each other's toes and stuff
and it this worked pretty well it was
just bigger more pressure um um but that
all and I think that seriousness in some
ways there's still humor but that
seriousness kind of infuses into the
game you feel it's a heavier game it's
the most cohesive product feeling I can
think of at scale that we've done as a
company the whole company was just
aligned and got it done I think back on
this experience and it was a really hard
time but I feel super grateful because
we were supported to make the very best
game that we possibly could um and given
the time to do it we're going to ship it
when it's done even when we made um
unreasonable promises about when that
might be in advance um and it was also
at a time before the game industry was
quite as specialized as it is now where
people got to wear multiple hats and
contribute in all the these different
ways so it was a rare life experience
and I'm really grateful to have been
part of it
[Music]
yeah man part of the fallout Fallout of
Half-Life 2 shipping was the realization
that we can't we can't do six- year long
bet the whole company bets over and over
again and all if we get it wrong one
time we're a big crater in the ground as
Gabe would say and so um we started to
think about episodic releases the first
idea when they pitched it to us like
we're going to do this episode of
content we'll do one every how how much
12 months yeah we were going to have
like alternating teams out every year
and a half something like that so I was
like yeah this is neat but then yeah it
just got out of hand so when they
decided to start playing with episodic
content the promise for me that I felt
was we can build smaller pieces denser
pieces faster and we know what we're
doing we're going to be really good at
this so a lot of it was like you know do
more with less like keep a bunch of the
existing stuff and and retweet it to
make some new interesting scenario like
probably the the biggest real new thing
for episode one as far as technology was
just having Alex with you throughout the
entire thing and having her behave in a
way that was believable and fun you know
she's with you at for a few distinct
Parts in halflife 2 but they're always
pretty heavily scripted and not really
in combat having her there and able to
actually be a useful companion that so
there's a lot of little tricks that we
did to to try to make that as fun as
possible for players she doesn't have
Supernatural knowledge he's not like
just finding things Without You lighting
them up but like if you throw a flare
out or you look at them with a
flashlight it's like okay she's going to
go for that Target because she can see
it we were like cranking on that and it
took forever like we were not just
partying and hanging out no I was I was
pretty much crunch that whole project I
think yeah we were crunch mode and then
same thing with episode 2 we started at
the same time as episode one uh and so
we ran for you know an extra year that
way which allowed us to um stretch um
and push push more so the hunters were
initially something that we wanted to
have a more sort of frenetic Pursuit uh
built into the design of the character
so it was really focused on at the time
creating a creature that could follow
the player into more types of spaces one
of the questions was how do we keep Alex
out of your way during this really
intense High action scene where the
player has agency to make whatever
decision they want about where they want
to be inside the house and that sort of
thing and that's when we got the idea to
have her sort of camp out by a window
and she would fire out the window and um
you know let you know if she saw any
hunters or soldiers out that window and
if uh the player started to spend time
at that window she would find another
one to go be at I mean so Dario casali
was um trying to create this final fight
in episode two The Stride is always
reminded me of attat in um Empire
Strikes Back um of course we wanted
something fresh because you know just
rocketing a ton of Striders wasn't going
to be be a bit repetitive after a while
so that's when we started collaborating
talking about the Magnuson device and
like yeah the hunters and like how how
would those all come together to make
this sort of an
overwhelming 25 30 minute battle set
piece
the citizens and the hunters and to a
lesser extent The Strider are all
secretly in cahoots to create this like
tension because like what we what we
always wanted was like got in the magnet
device on the last guy are you going to
be able to shoot it oh my God the
Rocket's going to be destroyed and then
like boom you hit it so that when
everyone comes out running you really
feel heroic you have you have the car
and you have a big space and you're not
guided anyway you just you have to go
and take care of this threat in a way
that you think is best um I think it it
pays off it makes the player feel like
oh you know I did this myself you know I
wasn't Guided by level designer at all
because we give them so many options
right we have you can you can kill the
hunters with driving the car into them
you can pick up a log and throw at them
you can pick up a Magnuson device and
throw it too soon and they'll shoot it
down you have to learn oh yeah I have to
kill the hunters first um you can use
Rockets to kill the hunters like you
have options and you have time and you
have space
but we dial the tension and the the
pacing up pretty slowly over
time y it is pretty cool the uh all the
the kind of cinematic destruction stuff
that happens in there it was it was so
hideously faked because basically you
would send a Strider who would do that
that sort of the low scuttling run and
he would just sit there and wait just
staring at this building until the
player could see the stride up the
building fr sit there
forever we dial the tension and the the
pacing up pretty slowly over time the
play tests we like the most is when The
Strider you know he's getting ready to
shoot the rocket and then the last
magnet and device goes off and then he's
done nice one Freeman we did it we held
them off like people were failing left
and right and the the the team the team
was calling for the map to be cut W I
took a lot of heat for that and both of
us did yeah we just we had to see it
through we were going to do an arc of
three of course because that's just how
you think of stories in those terms and
then you want the high point to come at
the end of the second one and Gabe at
one point saying who's the important
character you're going to kill I'm like
Lamar is going down this is going to be
it like I want the end I want episode
two to end with Lamar floating into
space and like everyone cries and gab's
like that's not good enough no no the
episodes were a lot of that was an
experiment on like what's the right
amount of episode episode 2 was longer
than episode one and bigger and people
like that better um but it also took
longer it took longer to make and people
didn't like it as much as they liked
halflife or halflife 2 kind of scope
right yeah so by saying episode are we
solving a lot of problems here or are we
just yeah uh making a sideways tradeoff
you know I think that's maybe the the
way I felt about it even into episode 3
I still don't know what that would have
been if we'd built it because it hadn't
been built that was the the feeling of
excitement of something I can't even
imagine is going to happen with as a
team I was not like imposing like a top
down this is what we must do to tell our
very important tale you know it's like
oh we have new features like how do we
use what kind of story can we do with
these now uh well I worked on episode
three and uh I was working on this gun
called The Ice gun that basically um let
you create amorphous uh shapes out of
ice um so you could like raise a little
ice wall in front of yourself it would
be attached to the floor and then the
combine soldiers could shoot holes in it
and it would shatter and and break like
kind of like glass I guess so that was
the primary mode of you you could build
Ledges for yourself to get down you know
Cliff faces it had another mode that was
like a kind of like a Silver Surfer mode
where you would extrude the ice in front
of yourself and and then run along it um
and use it to uh cross gaps go over
chasms and things like that what else do
we have it was set in the Artic cuz it
was around center around Borealis I
remember the little block
squishy oh yeah yeah Brian was working
on the uh the blobs um so we had the uh
the iso surfaces uh that we ended up
using in portal for the paint so we had
that as a um an enemy it was a blob
enemy and uh it could change its shape
and you could choreograph its shapes uh
with some content tools um and then uh
it could also split into little hoppy
blobs that could they were almost like
little head crabby things but they were
you know they were little Splats that
would hop around um we were doing all
kinds of stuff with that it could pass
through grates you know you could get
more gameplay out of something where you
had uh maybe a couple of creatures with
simpler behaviors oh yeah and then you
would spend time like uh combining them
and combining them with other game
mechanics story was never the boss of
anything it was always the you know we
worked on a peerto peer thing we were
all going to what can we do what do you
think would would be cool it was still a
collection of like playable levels in no
particular order uh and a collection of
story beats and story Concepts and and
uh we were still like probably another 6
months we would have had a critical mass
of like
mechanics um and then start putting them
in in a timeline I think probably year
and a half easily um you know depending
on how ambitious we got could have been
you know two and a half more years yeah
it's hard to be less a lot less than two
years yeah yeah yeah yeah I I think we
were six months in on it when we moved
to Left 4 Dead I don't know we were
moving at a pretty brisk Pace too I
thought that we needed to go much bigger
on episode 3 or do something else
because I don't know if this is the
right way to describe it but element
fatigue we I think we had really
explored a lot of what made sense in the
halflife universe and setting Arcane was
building the Raven home game and even
they were having trouble doing cool new
stuff with this tool set and like if
those guys can't figure out a bunch of
cool stuff to do with this I think we're
running out of fuel episode 3 is coming
along it's like well it's the new big
thing here we got it's got to be bigger
than all the stuff we just did you know
even episode two and it's like oh my God
you know it just becomes are we alled to
cry in this documentary that's what I
want to know left for dead needed um
kind of an all Hands-On sort of an
effort to ship um and so we put down ep3
to go help left for dead and it was uh
it was a really tight Shipping schedule
and it required a lot of work from
everybody to get out the door um and it
was worth it I mean it was left for dead
came out Left 4 Dead came out great um
but it took long enough and this is this
is the tragic and almost comical thing
about it was it took long enough that
then by the time we considered going
back to episode three the argument was
made like well we missed it it's too
late now you know and and we really need
to make a new engine and you know and to
continue the halflife series and all
that and now that just seems in
hindsight so wrong um you know we could
have definitely gone back and spent two
years to make episode three and you you
can't get lazy and say oh we're moving
the story forward that's that's coping
out of your obligation uh to Gamers
right yes of course they love the story
they love many many aspects of it but
sort of saying that your reason to do it
is because people want to know what
happens next you know we could have
shipped it like it wouldn't have been
that hard you know the failure
was my personal failure was being
stumped like I couldn't figure out why
doing episode 3 was was pushing anything
forward but yeah I mean some of those
people made Left 4 Dead two and then
portal two so yeah we did other things
instead it's not like that choice would
have been free right in terms of the
players like they may have gotten that
and not and given up something something
else yeah so it's hard to say but a lot
of us have been doing halflife for eight
plus years we saw a bunch of really
compelling reasons to go explore more
multiplayer based projects too because
not only just what player customers were
doing but internally you know we found
ourselves wanting to play a lot of
multiplayers it sounds silly to say it
cuz we're you know we're a relatively
big company that has a bunch of but
we're not that many people there's 300
something people here and so we're
working on a bunch of different projects
and it's like you know people are
passionate about portal people are
passionate about TF people are
passionate about Left 4 Dead and
halflife and you know Cs and DOTA uh
deadlock I mean there's a lot of things
there and you know I also work on our
Hardware so I've worked on Steam deck
and the original steam controller and
tiny bit on VR unfortunately for any
decision we make somebody's going to be
unhappy but hopefully we're making a
bunch of people happy with the choices
we do make if it weren't for the
episodes there'd be no such thing as
DOTA and I know that sounds really weird
but it was the things that we learned in
in developing the episodes that led to
you know Team Fortress to more rapid
updates I think everybody that worked on
halflife misses the working on that
thing but it's but it's also hard not to
be like man I am kind of I've seen every
way that you can fight an ant lion or uh
you know whatever and so you want to
like you know get some space away from
it until you can come back to it with
fresh eyes
it was easy to think about VR being a
vehicle for halflife because that was a
big technological innovation and kind of
a core reason for that product's
existence and I think like one of the
things we have internally tended to
attach to the half-life IP is innovation
gameplay Innovation is often times
enabled by a technological innovation
clearly there was a ton in halflife 1
and two uh and so yeah it's it's an
interesting challenge moving forward to
like think about what that means for
future halflife stuff for sure the
ending of half lifee Alex is somewhat a
self-critical realization so that was
super satisfying and all credit to to
the people who are specifically involved
in that decision and those sets of
designs I think that that Half-Life
represents a tool we have and promises
made to customers to capitalize on
Innovation and opportunities to build
game experiences that haven't been
involved previously and I think that
there are no shortage of those
opportunities facing us uh as industry
right
[Music]
now no fiddle sticks what now